Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the relationship
between exercise and weight loss.
And we start with a question:
can exercising in cool water
undermine weight loss
by leading to an increase in
post workout calorie intake?
Swimming and aquatic exercise
in general, are popular alternatives
to land-based activities
such as walking or biking.
The buoyancy helps take some
of the weight-bearing stress
off of joints,
but swimming appears to be
less effective for weight loss.
Obese women were randomized
into an hour a day
of walking, cycling, or swimming.
Six months later the walkers
lost an average of 17 pounds,
the cyclists lost
an average of 19 pounds,
and the swimmers
didn’t lose an ounce
(in fact, they actually
gained 5 pounds).
Gauging skin folds
to estimate body fat,
the measurements slimmed
more than 40 percent
in the walking
and cycling groups,
but there was no change at all
in the swimming group.
What’s going on?
And check this out.
The more the women walked,
the more they lost weight.
The more the women biked,
But the more laps they did
didn’t seem to matter.
Even an hour a day.
No weight loss.
What is going on?
Well, it turns out
that some exercise
boosts appetite
more than others.
While land-based exercise
does not stimulate
a compensatory increase
in appetite and calorie intake,
the same cannot be said
for water-based exercise.
In contrast to walking,
in contrast to running,
and in contrast
to cycling,
swimming can significantly
heighten hunger within hours.
This may explain why swimmers
tend to have more body fat
than runners of equal caliber,
even though they may be
actually expending more
calories during training.
If anything, you’d think
swimming might lead
to even greater weight loss since
you’re losing heat to the water.
But swimming didn’t
seem to work at all.
The cold, it turns out,
may actually be the culprit.
If you exercise
in warm water (about 90o F)
it does not boost your appetite
more than exercising on land.
After the same workout
in cool water (about 70° F),
people can end up eating
more than twice as much
at a meal an hour later.
Maybe they’re just burning off
extra calories to stay warm?
No, even at the same number
of calories expended,
people eat hundreds of calories
more after exercising in cold water.
Offered a buffet after burning off
about 500 calories in cool water,
people eat nearly 900 calories,
hundreds more than after exercising
in warm water
or just staying dry.
So, they ended up taking
in about twice as many
calories as they exercised off.
No wonder swimming doesn’t
appear useful for weight loss.
Would the same
thing happen
under different
temperatures on land?
A team of British researchers
sought to find out,
randomizing people
to briskly walk
for 45 minutes on a treadmill
in the cold (about 46° F)
or at closer to room
temperature (about 68° F).
Participants were then
presented with a buffet meal
in which their eating
was covertly recorded.
And calorie intake
was significantly greater
after exercising in the cold.
Though walking is often prescribed
for overweight individuals,
the researchers conclude,
“if walking was to take place
in a cold environment, such as in winter,
then this may stimulate food intake.”
In the warmer months,
though, obesity researchers
suggest exercising outdoors
may be preferable
to an air-conditioned gym.
All studies to date on the effects
of hot and cold environments
have found that exercising
in cool water or under cool conditions
on land led to an increase
in post-workout calorie intake.
What about a quick dip
in the pool after you exercise?
Australian researchers found
that immersion in water
for 15 minutes—cool or warm—
after a running session
resulted in increased
calorie intake.
What is it about getting
wet that whets your appetite?
Maybe they got
a chill after getting out
before they could change
into dry clothes?
This suggests that though
a cool shower after a workout
may be invigorating, it might
be better to stick to hot.
Next up, we look at what role inactivity
has played in the obesity epidemic.
Right now, almost 2/3 of
Americans are overweight.
And by 2030, more than
1/2 our population
may be clinically obese.
Childhood obesity
has tripled
and most of them will grow up
to be overweight as well.
The United States may be
in the midst of raising
the first generation since
our nation's founding
that will have a shorter
predicted life span than that
of the previous
generation.
The food industry
blames...
inactivity.
You just need
to move more.
But what is the role of exercise
in the treatment of obesity?
There's considerable debate
in the medical literature today
about whether physical activity
has any role whatsoever
in the epidemic of obesity that's
swept the globe since the 80s.
The increase in
calories per person
is more than sufficient to explain
the U.S. epidemic of obesity.
In fact, if anything, the
level of physical activity
over the last few decades
has actually gone up
in both Europe and
North America.
This has important
policy implications.
Yes, we still need
to exercise more,
but the priorities for reversing
the obesity epidemic
should focus on the
overconsumption of calories.
To work off the increased
caloric intake,
which for kids it's like an extra
can of soda and small fries,
compared to what they were
eating back in the 70s,
and for adults it's like
an extra Big Mac a day,
to work that off you'd have to
walk 2 hours a day, 7 days a week.
So exercise can prevent weight
gain, but the amount required
to prevent weight gain may be closer
to twice the current recommendations.
Public health advocates
have been experimenting
with including this
kind of information.
The fast-food menu
labeled with calories
and the number of miles to
walk to burn those calories
appeared to be most
effective in influencing
the selection of
lower calorie meals.
Now exercise alone may
have a small effect,
and that small effect can make a big
difference on the population scale.
A 1% decrease in BMI
nationwide might prevent
millions of cases of diabetes
and heart disease,
thousands of
cases of cancer...
But why don't we lose more
weight from exercise?
Maybe because we're just
not doing it enough.
The small magnitude of
weight loss observed
from the majority of
exercise interventions,
you know where they
make people exercise,
may be primarily due to
how low the doses are
of the prescribed
exercise.
People tend to over estimate
how many calories are burned
by physical
activity.
For example, there's this myth
that a bout of sexual activity
burns a few
hundred calories.
So, hey, you could get a
side of fries with that.
But if you actually
hook people up
and measure energy
expenditure during the act
and your study subjects don't get too
tangled up with all the wires and hoses,
though it may be merely the metabolic
equivalent of calisthenics,
given that the average bout of sexual
activity only lasts about 6 minutes,
a young man might expend approximately
21 calories during sexual intercourse.
Of course, he would've spent
roughly 1/3 of that
just lying around
watching t.v.–
just basal
metabolism.
So the incremental benefit is plausibly
on the order of 14 calories.
So maybe we could have,
like, 1 fry with that.
Finally today,
what’s more important:
diet or exercise when it
comes to weight loss.
You may be surprised
at the answer.
When trying to lose weight,
which is most important:
diet or exercise?
This is what a survey
found recently:
“The vast majority of those trying to
lose or maintain weight believe that
both monitoring food and beverage
consumption and physical activity
are equally important in weight
management and weight loss.”
Most people go with equally important,
and then exercise, and then diet.
And, most people are wrong.
Identified as one of the
most common misconceptions
about obesity in
this recent review,
the “Confusion about the leverage
of exercise on body weight.”
“Unfortunately, the
energy balance equation
[you know, calories in
have to equal calories out]
suggests that energy intake and energy
expenditure occupy equivalent roles
in determining energy balance,
when in fact the factors governing
energy intakes influence the
energy balance far more powerfully
than the factors determining
resting energy expenditure.”
What we put in our mouths
is most important.
For example, to walk off the calories
found in single pat of butter,
you’d have to add an extra 700
yards to your stroll that evening.
A quarter-mile jog for each
sardine we put in our mouth—
and that’s just the edible part.
And those who choose
to eat two chicken legs
better get out on
their own two legs,
and run an extra three miles
that day to outrun weight gain.
And that’s for steamed chicken;
skin removed.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.